Guide to the Carole De Saram Collection of Posters 1970-2002 PR 371
New-York Historical Society
Carole De Saram collection of posters
1970-2002
New-York Historical Society
De Saram, Carole
PR 371
7 Linear feet in 7 flat file folders.
This collection consists of posters from the 1970s-early 2000s, including promotional posters for events around New York City (particularly in Tribeca), posters concerning the women's movement of the 1970s, maps, movie and television advertisements, prints of artwork from earlier time periods, and calendars.
Arrangement
The posters are arranged with posters related to New York City (mainly Tribeca) first, followed by reproductions of artwork and advertisements for art shows, then movie and television posters, then assorted miscellaneous posters and calendars. Posters related to the women's movement, which were donated after the bulk of the collection was processed, are found at the end of the container list, together in one folder.
Biographical / Historical
Carole De Saram was a community organizer and activist in the 1970s and 1980s. A longtime Tribeca resident, she served as both the Chair of Manhattan Community Board 1 and the President of the Tribeca Community Association. She worked diligently to improve living conditions in Tribeca and to keep the community safe and engaged, as well as to get Tribeca landmarked as a historic district. De Saram was also an avid feminist, and served as President of the National Organization for Women's New York City Chapter.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was donated by Carole De Saram in May and July 2018. An additional thirteen posters (noted in the container list) were donated in 2020-21.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also owns the Carole De Saram papers, which were donated by De Saram in 2016 and contain records of her work as a community organizer in Tribeca.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of over 50 posters from the 1970s-early 2000s collected by Carole De Saram. These are primarily related to events in New York City and Tribeca, as well as popular culture, including movies, art exhibitions, and political conferences. Several of the posters relate to the women's movement of the 1970s-1980s. Some of the posters are reproductions of earlier artwork, and there are also some wall calendars and maps.
American movies.; Art -- Exhibitions -- Posters.; Community organization.; Feminism.; TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.); Calendars.; Maps.; Posters.
- Hagstrom Map. "New York City: Manhattan House Numbers and Transit Guide" (Oversize), circa 1970s (Folder Flat File Oversize, Folder 6)
- Americana '75 Street Fair Poster, 1975 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Designed by Richard Bernstein and sponsored by American Airlines. Fair held on 52nd street, from Broadway East to 3rd Avenue.
- Burger King New York Yankees Poster, 1978 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Poster with printed drawings by Frank Becerra of the team members.
- "Community Board #1: Borough of Manhattan Presents 'Use of Toxins in an Urban Environment'" Poster, 1983 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Promotional poster for event, with artwork by Mario Pikus on the dangers of fumigating with methyl bromide.
- Tribeca Benefit Art Auction Poster (2 copies), 1986 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Features drawing of eagle by Mimi Gross.
- The Texture of Tribeca Promotional Poster, 1989 (Folder Flat File, Folder 3)
  Poster to promote Andrew Scott Dolkart's illustrated history of Tribeca, The Texture of Tribeca.
- Uprooting Poverty Through Community Development Conference Poster, 1990 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  In honor of the 25th anniversary of the Pratt Center for Environmental Development. Artwork by Lorenz.
- Operation Welcome Home--NYC Poster, 1991 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  Promotional poster for parade honoring Persian Gulf War veterans. Artwork by Milton Glaser.
- "Celebrating Historic Preservation: Civic Fame: Municipal Building, City of New York"", 1992 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  Municipal buiding statue renovation. Published by Mayor David Dinkins's office during his mayoral tenure. Photograph by Gaston Dubois.
- "An Axonometric View of the 'Triangle Below Canal'", 1994 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  Aerial map of Tribeca by Ludington Ltd..
- New York City Marathon Poster, 1995 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Very colorful promotional poster, designed by Peter Max.
- "Listening to the City" Town Hall Event at Jacob Javits Center, 2002 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  3 identical posters from "Listening to the City" event held at Jacob Javits Center, July 20, 2002. Project of Civic Alliance to Rebuild Downtown New York. Includes various images depicting development of lower Manhattan from colonial period to the World Trade Center. Donated March 2020 and added to collection in October 2020.
- Street Map of Tribeca (2 copies), Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 3)
  Copies of Tribeca map from before the Battery Park City landfill was completed in 1976.
- Dioxin/Agent Orange Exposure Poster, Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Informational poster released by the New York State Temporary Commission on Dioxin Exposure. The poster has two business cards for Vietnam Veterans of America offices in New York City stapled to it.
- "New York Needs You--Join The Auxiliary Police", Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Designed by "Schlamp," for New York City Police Foundation.
- Layered Print of Swan and Heron, 1982 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  Print by "J. Yelton" (?).
- New Deal Art Golden Anniversary Posters (5), 1988 (Folder Flat File, Folder 2)
  Posters feature prints of Lily Furedi's Subway, LaVerne Nelson Black's Jicarilla "Apache Fiesta", Jenne Magafan's The Windmill, O. Louis Guglielmi's Martyr Hill, and Ilya Bolotowsky's In The Barber Shop.
- Print of The Graham Children, 1990 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  By William Hogarth.
- Tight Lacing, Or Fashion Before Ease, Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Replica poster of the original satirical print by John Collet.
- Print of Painting Depicting Animals, Columns, and Pyramids, Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 3)
  Painting originally by English artist Julie Arkell.
- Treasures of Tutankhamun Exhibit Poster, 1976 (Folder Flat File, Folder 2)
  Distributed by the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
- Nut Tree Art Exhibition Posters (2), 1971, 1977 (Folder Flat File, Folder 3)
  Includes "Coit Tower, San Francisco," watercolors by Cecile Johnson and an image from "Batiks by Winifred Madison."
- Star Trek Collage Poster, 1976 (Folder Flat File, Folder 2)
  Of photographs from the original television show.
- Star Wars: Return of the Jedi Poster, 1983 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
- Star Trek V: The Final Frontier Poster, 1989 (Folder Flat File, Folder 2)
- Mission: Impossible Apple Poster, 1996 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Reads, "YOUR MISSION: BEGINS AT HTTP://WWW.MISSION.APPLE.COM/," with a picture of Tom Cruise.
- Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone Movie Poster, 2001 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
- The Day After Tomorrow Movie Poster, 2004 (Folder Flat File Oversize, Folder 6)
- Lunar/Chinese New Year Calendar, 1984 (Folder Flat File, Folder 4)
  Produced by Chinese Native Products and Pearl River Chinese Products Emporium, with Chinese art prints and advertisements for "Bee and Flower" soap on the pages inside.
- Dias Santos Calendar, 1997 (Folder Flat File, Folder 2)
  With guide to Mexican religious imagery printed on the back.
- Presidents of the United States Poster, circa 1980s (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Distributed by Bayside Fuel Oil Corp, with biographical information about each president printed on the back.
- Elvis Presley--Las Vegas Poster, 1976 (Folder Flat File, Folder 2)
- "Conservation: keeping America's neighborhoods together", 1981 (Folder Flat File, Folder 1)
  Promotional poster for Preservation Week, published by the National Trust for Historic Preservation.
- New York State Fair Poster, 1984 (Folder Flat File, Folder 5)
  Reproduction of poster from 1903 New York State Fair in Syracuse.
- "Born Free" Halmark Poster, Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 3)
  Poster with "Born Free" lyrics, written by Don Black and John Barry, and an African savannah landscape underneath.
- The New Game of Human Life (2 copies), Undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 3)
  Reprints of the 1790 game.
- "Women Unite!", 1970-1971 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  2 posters. The first is an original "Women Unite!" poster with artwork signed "Jeannie Friedman, Newark, 1970." This poster was used to glue on the words "National Organization for Women" across the top; the word "Organization" is missing now. From this the second poster, a reproduction, was made and used, according to the donor, at City National Bank for "Close Account Day" in 1971. (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)
- "Women's March for Equality", 1971 August 26 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  Poster for march beginning on Fifth Avenue at 44th Street and going to rally at 72nd Street mall, New York City. Seeking "Our rights to: abortion, political power, child care centers, equality under the law, equal education and employment." With women's power logo. (Donated and added to the collection in March 2021.)
- "I want you...For the Navy", 1973 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  Issued by the U.S. Government Printing Office. Artwork by Howard Chandler Christy, 1917. (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)
- "Infonavit – Ano Internacional De La Mujer, Programa Cultural - Junio de 1975" (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  The poster text includes the program of events for June 21-30, 1975. In Spanish. (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)
- "Good Carpenters", 1976 June 15 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  Poster of poem "Good Carpenters" by Erica Jong, with small drawing. Presentation note on poster indicates it was done by Jong for Betty Friedan on the occasion of the publication of her book "It Changed My Life" and presented to Friedan by Carole de Saram, Muriel Fox, Elinor Guggenheimer, Elizabeth Forsling Harris, Eleanor Holmes Norton, Marlene Sanders, Ellen Sulzberger Straus, Mary Jean Tully. Paul Freeman, scribat. (Donated and added to the collection in March 2021.)
- "Marilyn" [Monroe], 1977 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  Artwork by J.B. Printed in Scotland. Minerva Denmark/Switzerland. (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)
- "The Urban Woman", 1978 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  Poster for conference held by the New York Chapter of the National Organization for Women, October 21-22, 1978, at Washington Irving High School in Manhattan. Poster text includes the program of speakers, panels, and topics. (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)
- "Judy Chicago. The Birth Project", circa 1984 (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  Artwork is an embroidery from the Project by Pamella Nesbit. Text includes reference to "other creative visions by Judy Chicago." (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)
- "Women of the Forth World. NEW-Movement for a New Community. New-York. Paris. London", undated (Folder Flat File, Folder 7)
  With text echoing Sojourner Truth, ending in "Am I not a woman?" (Donated and added to the collection in November 2020)